<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Severall letters betwixt the French king and the q. mother, concerning the present troubles there vnto which is added, the French king's declaration vpon the departure of the queene mother, and monsieur his brother out of the kingdome : the confirmation of the court parliament of Paris vpon the same / faithfully translated out of the French.</title>
            <author>Louis XIII, King of France, 1601-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16847.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1347</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22136737</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22136737</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1230</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68416)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1230)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1731:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Severall letters betwixt the French king and the q. mother, concerning the present troubles there vnto which is added, the French king's declaration vpon the departure of the queene mother, and monsieur his brother out of the kingdome : the confirmation of the court parliament of Paris vpon the same / faithfully translated out of the French.</title>
                  <author>Louis XIII, King of France, 1601-1643.</author>
                  <author>Marie de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry IV, King of France, 1573-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath. Butter, and Nich. Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D².</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 14 and 19 misnumbered 12 and 29 respectively.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marie de Médicis, --  Queen, consort of Henry IV, King of France, 1573-1642.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIII, 1610-1643.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1230:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1230:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SEVERALL LETTERS BETWIXT THE FRENCH KING AND THE Q. MOTHER, Concerning the preſent Troubles there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vnto which is added,</hi> The French Kings Declaration vpon the departure of the Queene Mother, and Monſieur his Brother out of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The Confirmation of the Court Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> vpon the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully tranſlated out of the French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for NATH: BVTTER, and NICH: BOVRNE. 1631.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="correspondence">
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:1230:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1230:2"/>
               <head>A LETTER OF THE FRENCH KING TO THE QVEENE MOTHER.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madame:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot ſufficiently teſtifie my griefe, for having underſtood by your Letters and by the report of my Couſin the Marſhall of <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and of the Lord of <hi>Roijſſy,</hi> the refuſall which you have made of all the conditions I have offred you, for the change of your abode at <hi>Campeigne,</hi> into ſome more convenient place for your ſelfe, and leſſe ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected for me. Were it not a thing altogether neceſſary for the welfare of my affaires, I would not have cauſed you ſo much to have beene preſſed thereabout. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have reſerved to my ſelfe to give you ſhortly to underſtand the laſt reſolution which I have taken upon ſo important a buſineſſe, I will ſay no more thereof to you at this preſent, but will anſwere onely to that which you have written in your laſt concerning my ſaid Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin the Marſhall of <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and the ſaid Lord of <hi>Roijſſy.</hi> It had beene very difficult for mee to have ſent you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of more approved honeſty; and the report which they made me of your intention at their returne from
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1230:3"/>you, is ſo agreeable to the ſenſe of theſe Letters you writ unto me by my ſayd Couſin the Marſhall of <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Roijſſy,</hi> as you have no occaſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to complaine; but I rather, becauſe my inſtant and reiterated prayers have had ſo little power to worke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you. God will inſpire into me, if it be his pleaſure, what I ought to doe for the good and quiet of my eſtate. After the which I ſhall alwayes have the ſame conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of you, which you can expect Madame, from</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble and obeiſant Sonne, <hi>LOVIS.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Fontainebelleau,</hi> 
                     <date>28. May, 1631.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="reply">
               <head>Anſwer of the Queene Mother to the Kings Letter above-written.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Monſieur my Sonne:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Had deferred to have written you an anſwere to your Letter the <hi>28.</hi> of this Moneth, had not mine enemies ſpred a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour to my preiudice, that I was eſcaped into Flanders. This ſhall aſſure you, that I am yet here, reſolved not to depart hence, unleſſe it bee by force, if this be not to vpbraid you with with the reſpect which a good Mother, ſuch as I am to you, ought to be in with her Sonne; for I never had nor ſhall have the deſire to retire my ſelfe into any place where you have not abſolute-power, having (God be thanked) no crime vpon my Conſcience which ſhould give mee occaſion to withdraw my ſelfe thence, nor which ought to hinder me from hoping; that your goodneſſe weary of ſeeing me thus to ſuffer, will oblige you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1230:3"/>in the end to reſtore me to the calme which is due to mine inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency; moſt humbly beſeeching you to vouchſafe, that for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to your laſt vpon this occaſion, I may tell you, that if I had no other conſideration of remaining here, but mine owne, I would long ſince have rendred you that obedience which you require at my hands, of departing hence. But if you pleaſe to conſider what thoſe diſpleaſures are of a Mother ſo afflicted as I am, without having committed any fault againſt You or your eſtate; you may eaſily Iudge, how unſeemely it would be both to you and me, that me continuall teares and my extreame affliction ſhould be expoſed to the eyes of your Subiects in ſo long a Iourney, I ſhould have to make vnto any one of thoſe places which you have caus'd to be propounded vnto me, and that the triumph of mine enemies ſhould be adorned with this ſpectacle, which would be moſt proper to illuſtrate their power all the world over, and the miſerable eſtate whereto I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. If the counſels which are given you vpon this ſubiect, came not from the ſame perſons which have perſwaded you to confine me to this place, and who doth not thinke (knowing me ſo well as they doe, to be ſubiect to ſtoppings of breath, whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I am ſicke) that I can live <hi>3.</hi> dayes to an end; You might well know that it is farre more important for your ſtate, that the ill vſage which I ſuffer without cauſe be concealed heere within foure walles, then made knowne to every one in my paſſage; nor would you be ſo earneſt after it in your ſaid Letter, nor ſo much complaine of my refuſall of doing it. I know well what duty I owe vnto you as you are my King; but you alſo as my Sonne ought to compaſsionate mine afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and not to alledge vnto mee alwayes as you doe, the conſiderations of your eſtate, ſeeing there is no man that knowes not right well that mine abode here can bring no preiudice therunto, &amp; that this is none other pretext or artifice; then that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1230:4"/>which was vſed by others heretofore, during our former ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for which you were ſo ſorie, ſo ſoone as you were come home to your ſelfe, after the death of the Conſtable <hi>LVYNES,</hi> and which is now put in practiſe to torment me; to the end that looſing (as I doe) my repoſe, my health may be ſo impaired, as I muſt ſinke vnder the burthen, and looſe my life, which they cannot any longer indure.</p>
               <p>As touching the Conditions which have beene offred me, I doubt not, but they have told you, and would make it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to be beleeved, that they are very advantageous vnto me: But if they would deſcribe them as they ought, there would be no ſuch Iudgement made; ſeeing that <hi>MOVLINS</hi> and <hi>ANGERS</hi> which have beene propounded vnto me for mine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode, are ſo infected with the Plague, as without doubt they have bin choſen by them of purpoſe to thruſt me into the iawes of death, which they ſee, doth not ſeize vpon me heere ſo ſoone as they could wiſh. Your diſpoſition is too good to conſent to their wicked deſignes, in caſe you know them: but vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of the duty which you owe to your eſtate is hidden the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which they would have me ſwallow, to ridde their hands of me, contrary to your intention: God will deliver you from that, and your Mother alſo, if he pleaſe, and will touch your heart, to make you know, that next your owne ſelfe I am the perſon moſt intereſted in your preſervation, and that for this purpoſe, my life imports you more than my ſelfe. There is no honeſt man in your Kingdome that doth not thinke ſo. For the honeſty of my Conſin the Marſhall <hi>de Schomberg</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in your Letters, I leave the iudgement thereof to God, and doe beſeech his divine Maieſty, to grant both him and me the grace, that his counſels may be ſuch as hee is bound in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to give you, and that hee will inſpire alſo into you that which you ought to doe, for the good and repoſe of your eſtate,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1230:4"/>aſſuring my ſelfe, if you follow thoſe divine inſpirations in ſtead of the paſsionate counſels against me which you have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ere-while; your eſtate ſhall therein finde quiet and ſafety, and I the comfort which is ſo neceſſary for mee, and thoſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of love which I ought to expect from you</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Monſieur my Sonne,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your moſt humble, and moſt affectionate Mother and ſubject, MARIE.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From</hi> Campeigne <date>
                        <hi>this laſt of</hi> May, <hi>1631.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Copie of a Letter written from <hi>PARIS</hi> 
               <date>the <hi>7.</hi> of August, <hi>1631.</hi>
               </date>
            </head>
            <p>VPon Monday laſt, the Queene Mother ſent hither the Lord <hi>De Beno'ville</hi> with letters to the Parliament, and to the Sheriffes of this City. And hee delivered both the one and the other in open and full Aſſembly, and afterward departed againe without contradiction. Theſe letters were preſently ſent to the Kings Majeſty without being opened. It is confidently reported, that the ſaid Letters are manifeſtly repleniſhed with very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely and ſtrange threatnings. Thereupon, and upon the arrivall of an Ambaſſador from <hi>Bruxels,</hi> the Kings Majeſty having changed his purpoſe concerning his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of our Lady of <hi>Lieſſe,</hi> is now expected heere in very few dayes to enter into the ſaid Parliament: there
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1230:5"/>to open his Declarations againſt the ſaid Queene and <hi>Monſieur.</hi> It is confidently held that hee will reſtore the <hi>Paulette,</hi> to the Officers of the Court according to the ancient forme and cuſtome.</p>
            <p>The farther wee doe proceed, the more the diviſions of this Court doe increaſe and waxe worſe. The jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies which have heere beene conceived concerning the ſame, have cauſe order to be given for the augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reinforming of the old Regiments, and Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to be granted for 10000. Foot forces more, and 20. Cornet of Horſe.</p>
            <p>The Kings Majeſty hath given Charge and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Monſieur <hi>de Guyſe, De Gramont,</hi> to the Earle of <hi>Rochefoucault,</hi> and to Monſieur <hi>de Valencay,</hi> with all ſpeed and diligence to be preſent with his Majeſty. The laſt of theſe (as wee are informed) hath given a flat denyall, that hee will not depart out of <hi>Calais.</hi> And if <hi>Monſieur</hi> bee ſure enough without, as wee are certified that he ſhall be, it is very credible that the reſt will bee no leſſe refracto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but draw backe as well as he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Kings brother hath put away and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged one of his Secretaries, and three of his other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, who were by the Lord — <hi>Coigneux</hi> ſuſpected of Treaſon. He is yet at <hi>Beyancon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee have received Letters from <hi>Bruxels,</hi> that <hi>Forſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh</hi> and <hi>Altringer,</hi> are about to joyne their Forces vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe Troupes of the Adminiſtrator of <hi>Wirtenbergh,</hi> who ſo miſerably is fallen away from the Concluſion made at the Dyet at <hi>Leypſich.</hi> Since wee have beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of this Deſigne, concerning the forenamed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, word was ſent to Monſieur <hi>de la Force,</hi> to put the Army of <hi>Champeigne</hi> into the Field, but hee anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1230:5"/>that as yet it is not expedient.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>de Loraine,</hi> hath ſent hither the Lord <hi>de Ville,</hi> to make knowne to his Majeſty, that <hi>Loraine</hi> is at his Devotion, and that if the Gates of <hi>Nancy</hi> are not large and great enough, the very walles ſhall bee broken downe, to give entrance to, and to receive his Majeſty. But all their kind of ſubmiſſions will not purge and cleere his Highneſſe. Who is like enough to receive the firſt ſtroake of the forces of this eſtate; If ſo bee that the ſaid Lord doe but enterprize any thing, and eſpecially, if hee doe give entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into his company to the Prince of <hi>Phalsbourgh,</hi> who (as it is reported) for a certaine, is one of his parties.</p>
            <p>The forenamed Ambaſſador of <hi>Bruxels,</hi> comes to make excuſe to his Majeſty in that the <hi>Infanta</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken on a ſuddaine could not afford that due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reſpect to the Queene Mother, which otherwiſe ſhe would have done.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of <hi>Straesburgh,</hi> much ſorrowing at the miſerable and unfaithfull falling of the Duke of <hi>Wirtenbergh,</hi> doe now earneſtly implore the ſuccour and aid of our King by the Lord <hi>Clafer.</hi> His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty hath given him all aſſurance, that hee will in no wiſe forſake them. God grant that he may returne home better contented than the Ambaſſador of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi> Who much grieved, that he could not receive grant of 4000. men which he required: will within few dayes returne home very ill ſatisfied. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe he hath received the gift of a Chaine of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, worth the value of five thouſand Crownes. The Lord <hi>Larſon,</hi> Treaſurer of the ſaid King of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1230:6"/>
               <hi>Sweden</hi> received a Chaine of two thouſand Florens, and the ſecretary of the ſaid Embaſſador, had one given him of one thouſand.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>De Villars</hi> hath ſould the Government of <hi>Honfleur</hi> to the Marquis <hi>De Sourdis,</hi> from whom it is like to be taken away. He was lately brought in queſtion and accuſed before the King that his Company of the Guard was not compleat and that he purſed up the Monies of thoſe that were more to pay. Whereupon, and by reaſon of ſome Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent words which he gave in the preſence of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, his Maieſty plucked from his neck his Corſlet and degraded him, and diſarmed him moſt ſhamefully in open Company.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="correspondence">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1230:6"/>
            <head>A Letter written by the Queene Mother to the Kings Maieſty with the Anſwere of his Maieſty to the ſame.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Letter of the Queene Mother to the King.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir. My Sonne.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Have thought it my duty diligently to acquaint you by my Lord <hi>De la Barre</hi> that I am departed from <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigne,</hi> as alſo to declare unto you the reaſons and Motives inciting me thereunto which your Maieſty ſhall find in this Letter.</p>
               <p>If I ſhould alledge no more, but the hardneſſe and harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my impriſonment, the continuall diſquiets and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions which I ſuffered by the Cardinall <hi>Richelieu,</hi> I thinke they might eaſily be of power to give abundant ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to your good diſpoſition, for I know that your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination is ſuch that you would not have me obey him to the very preiudice of my life. And to the preiudice of your pious affection to your Mother, which can no longer be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, nor conſiſt with my obedience to him in this place, eſpecially when all thoſe evills and wrong inflicted vpon me, are pretended to be done in your name. I have hitherto (without expreſſe of my griefe, and relating of my teares) ſuffered that which were impoſsible for a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a far ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ranck and degree, to ſuffer with any kind of patience. I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1230:7"/>have beene held from the firſt beginning as guilty, becauſe I would not obey the Cardinals pleaſure, for this the moſt veritable letter beares it, being the firſt declaration addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from <hi>Champaigne</hi> to the Parliaments and Provinces. Since that I have beene uſed and dealt withall, as if I were the greateſt Enemy of the whole Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> not onely in the deniall of my honeſt and iuſt requeſts, but even in the miſconſtruing of my good meaning and intentions. And in ſhutting up in priſon my officers and ſervants as well as my owne perſon. Inſomuch that they might not budge out of the City without his warrant, that kept and guarded me with two Companies of foot Souldiers 500. Horſmen, and unanſwerable to all my ſubmiſsions, and the lenity and mildneſſe which I manifeſted in all my treaties and proceedings with you, I have beene oppoſed and ſet upon with nothing but threatnings, violences, and inſultings; Which undoubtedly and infallibly, (if you reſpect my natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſpoſition) would have by this time enterred me in my Tomb, if the Lord of heaven himſelf had not ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my courage with a magnanimous and generous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and in recompence of my candid and faire procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I have beene repaid with tricks and diſsimulations. The forces that were brought upon the borders of <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigne</hi> were onely retired thither to abuſe thoſe good people that did ſympathize with my Impriſonment, and under ſhew of the liberty which I had yeelded me to walk abroad, to ſurpriſe me as it were in Ambuſh. As I have bin well enformed by ſuch as could eaſily know ſomething concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the evill intention of the Cardinall againſt me, to prolong my miſery, and to keepe the people and ſtrangers in ſuſpence and expectation. There have beene ſent unto me divers Embaſſadors, who noyſed abroad, that they came
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1230:7"/>to allay all difference and amend the matter. But, O God! What remedy and amendment did they ſpeake of to me? When as ſome of them have bin ſo inſolent that violating the honour and reſpect due unto me as did the Marſhall of <hi>Schomb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgh,</hi> greedily raging after me untill the very entrance of my bedchamber. The laſt voyage which my Couſin the Marſhall <hi>Deſtree</hi> made, and the Lord <hi>Meſmin</hi> was no better than the former, for it was onely to threaten me with the returning againe of my guard and againe to make me feare the former violence, and the loſſe of my faithfull officers and ſervants, neceſſary for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my life; And to yeeld my ſelfe to their proceedings, God knowes to what end and intention. As alſo to propound unto me the iourney of going to <hi>Chartres</hi> or to <hi>Mante</hi> where you might ſee me before I went into <hi>Champaigne.</hi> Which cauſed me to ſuſpect their propoſition, <hi>Champaign</hi> being the way, but not <hi>Chartres.</hi> But this was more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and agreeable to their deſire which they had, to leade me along in Triumph, and ſhew, and with me all <hi>Europe,</hi> where my Children command and raigne, more then our mutuall meeting, which I deſire more than any thing, the privation whereof is the greateſt and moſt ſenſible miſery which I ſuffer, how ever the other are cruell enough. All theſe things I have ſuffered with reſignation, to teſtifie to the whole Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> that I did reſpect your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority even in the hands of my Enemies, and that I neuer had nor ſhall have, any but wholeſome and good intentions toward your State, for having matter and ſubiect enough to compaine of, I contained my ſelfe with all patience fiue monethes together, to give you leaſure to find out and acknowledge my integrity and innocency. And to let it appeare unto you, that I never had intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1230:8"/>nor held Correſpondency with any of my Children but your owne ſelfe. However the Cardinall maliciouſly hath poſseſſed and perſwaded you to the contrary, to the end that he might attaine to the accompliſhment of his owne wicked deſires and intentions. Which is, to chaſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell both Mother and Children, out of the Kingdome, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the end of his deſignes, and one day you will find it and acknowledge the ſame, perhaps when it will be to late.</p>
               <p>In meane while, now how as the time of my ſufferings hath continued long, a new to give you an impreſsion of my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and that longer time would make me to be eſteemed guilty, if I did not now have a care for the preſervation of my life, and the reeſtabliſhment of my liberty ſeeing that my Children cannot diſpence with the diſgrace and Infamy which ſhould be laid upon me. That ſhall notwithſtanding, (by Gods grace) iuſtifie me in the mind and before the face of all the world, for as I have perceived that my body did decreaſe, and my ſtrength was daily abated and I daily weakned, and that it was the intention of the Cardinall to have me die within foure walles; I was then reſolved to ſave my life and reputation and to give ſome eaſement to my ſorrowes and ſufferings. Wherfore I will accept of that good offer made unto me by the <hi>Marquis de Verdes,</hi> who every day ſince my departure, hath wiſhed me to goe to the <hi>Capelle</hi> of which he is Governour, which is a place where your Mai: hath abſolute power, I was then reſolved to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take my ſelfe thither, &amp; was not come within three leagues from that place, but the ſaid Lord <hi>De Vardes</hi> ſends me word by two Gentlemen, one of which was the Knight his brother, that I could not enter into the ſaid <hi>Capelle,</hi> and that he had delivered up the ſaid place into the hands of his Father. I beſeech you to conſider how I was grieved and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1230:8"/>anxious, when after that I found my ſelfe thus baſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, I found alſo my ſelfe earneſtly purſued by the Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie whereupon I was adviſed to preſſe forward and to goe forth of your Kingdome. Inſomuch that I was conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to iourney thirty leagues without either eating or drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. And it hath beene Gods pleaſure in this occaſion, as in others alſo that the cunning devices ſhould be diſcovered even by the mouth of ſuch as were agents. Who have in ſome manner confeſſed that the ſaid Cardinall had plotted the buſineſſe and onely intending to make me to ſtye and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon your ſtate, which was that which he onely deſired &amp; that which I only feared. Being th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reduced &amp; brought to this miſerable extreamity, I have betaken my ſelfe into this place of <hi>Avennes</hi> which belongs to the Archdutcheſse, being conſtrained in a ſtrange Countrey to ſeeke my liberty and ſafety and protection of my life, which I thought eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have found in ſome place under your obedience. But what was ſo faithfully profered me, was ſhamefully refuſed me, and as now I perceiue was meerely offered unto me by the ſtratagemes and deviſes of my Enemies, rather then in any good intention to receive me. Now I ſeeke nothing but onely the confident truſt upon Iuſtice and equity, which you deny not to the moſt miſerable and meaneſt of all your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects. After the ſame ſhall have quitted and iuſtified me, although my Enemies ſhould receive no other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but the ſhame of tormenting and perſecuting me, with the declaracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their iniuſtice, yet this wil then hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all farther evils which might accrew, and it will cauſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints of my other Children to ceaſe, who have ſome intereſt in my ſorrowes by reaſon of their owne reputation, and will give ſatisfaction to all <hi>Europe,</hi> &amp; lay an obſtacle to whatſoever hereafter may be plotted againſt me.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:1230:9"/>
               <p>For mine owne part I ſhould not much care but reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to ſacrifice the remnant of my dayes, unto the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of the Cardinall, were it not that I deſire to make up the breach, and to eſtabliſh the union and concord betweene your ſelfe and my ſonne. <hi>D'Orleans</hi> which he hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy overthrowne, in your mind by his ſeverall deviſes. You may if you pleaſe yeeld a remedy againſt this great evill, and hinder any worſe proceeding by your good Iudgment and underſtanding. If I may be ſo happy, as to returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to you, I promiſe faithfully, I will cauſe you to know, that in any thing I ought, I have never eſteemed any dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then your good and Vtility.</p>
               <closer>Since I am <salute>MONS: my Sonne.</salute> 
                  <signed>Your moſt humble, and moſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioned Mother and ſubiect MARIE</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Avennes</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>the 21. Iuly 1631.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="reply">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:1230:9"/>
               <head>Anſwer of the King to the Letter of the Queene his Mother.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAME,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am ſo much the more moued at your reſolution, which you haue taken, to abſent your ſelfe from this State and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by how much you had leſſe ground and cauſe. The ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary impriſonment, the ſuppoſed perſecutions which you complaine of, the apprehenſions which you confeſſe your ſelfe to haue conceiued in <hi>Campagnie</hi> concerning your life; they haue no more foundation, than the purſuite which you ſay was made after you at your departure, and the intelligence which you write vntome, hath beene held with the onely Sonne of the Lord <hi>de Vardes.</hi> Their intentions are a deuice ſomewhat like vnto that feare, which you fained to haue three moneths agoe, that I would ſend you backe againe into <hi>Italic,</hi> which you know I neuer thought, much leſſe euer intended. For thoſe proffers which I haue made you, of diuers and ſeuerall dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and habitations, farre remote from thoſe parts, can teſtifie the contrary. Such calumnies and accuſations ſhall not (God be bleſſed) diſgrace and diſ-repute me in Chriſtendome, where my actions do ſufficiently make me knowne. Whatſoeuer you tell me of thoſe that ſerue me and are neere vnto me, hath not ſo much as an appearance of truth. And I wonder and am euen aſtoniſhed, that the Authors of your letters are not aſhamed, to ſet before your eyes ſuch things againſt thoſe, vnto whom your conſcience knowes, that ſuch things cannot be imputed. I doe perceiue and know by manifold infallible proofes, the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and ſincerity of my Couſen the Cardinall of <hi>Richel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> His religious obedience which hee affords mee, his faithfull care concerning whatſoeuer doth concerne my perſon and eſtate, ſpeakes for him. If you pleaſe, <hi>Madame,</hi> you ſhall permit and giue me leaue to tell you, that the action which you haue ſo lately done, and what hath paſſed not long ſince, cauſeth that I cannot be ignorant what hath beene your intention hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and what I may expect in the time to come. The reſpect
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1230:10"/>which I bare you makes me forbeare of ſaying any thing more vnto you. I pray the Lord in the meane while to giue you good counſell, And that you may alwayes preuaile, with his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons who ſhall alwayes be</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madame,</salute> 
                  <signed>Yours</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>The French Kings Declaration vpon the departure of the Queene his Mother, and Monſieur his Brother, out of the Kingdome.</head>
            <head type="sub">Confirmed at the Parliament at <hi>Paris</hi> 
               <date>the <hi>13.</hi> day of <hi>Auguſt 1631.</hi>
               </date> faithfully tranſlated out of the French Copy.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>LEwis</hi> by the grace of God King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Nanarre,</hi>
               </signed>
               <salute>to all thoſe vnto whom theſe preſents ſhall come, greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Wee haue by our Letters of Declaration, the 30. of March laſt paſt, publiſhed throughout our whole Kingdome, for the cauſes contained therein, declared all thoſe guiltie of <hi>Crimen laſa Maieſtatis,</hi> who abuſing the facility of our wel belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and onely Brother the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> did by their euill deuices and pernicious counſels, intice and perſwade him to withdraw himſelfe from vs, and to depart out of our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome without our knowledge and permiſſion, as alſo all thoſe that ſhould be found to be his followers, if in a certaine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed time they did not take recourſe to our Grace and Mercie, hauing hoped by this meanes to giue them leiſure to find out and acknowledge their fault, and ſo to reduce them vnto their duties, and thereby cauſe them to depart and abſtaine from all euill wayes and practiſes, which they had begun, as well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as without the Kingdome, to trouble the reſt and peace of the ſame. But in ſtead of vſing this meanes to repent them of their fault, and to take their refuge to our clemencie and fauour, they haue perſiſted in their euill counſels, and carried away
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1230:10"/>our Brother (againſt the duty of his birth, and the reſpect which hee oweth vs) and inſtigated him to write vnto vs let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters full of bitterneſſe, calumnies, impoſtures and accuſations againſt the Adminiſtration and Gouernment of our State; ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and aiming by thoſe ſaid letters, full of injuries and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (with other writings of the like nature, which they haue cauſed to be printed euery where) to perſwade our people to bee ill conceited of vs, and by them and other Princes our neighbours, to haue ſiniſter opinions of our affaires and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, accuſing (againſt all truth and reaſon) our welbeloued Couſin the Cardinal <hi>Richelieu</hi> of infidelitie, and of enterprizing againſt our perſon, and the perſon of our much honoured Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his owne, and our Eſtate; as alſo ſome others which wee do employ in our Gouernment (euen about the moſt weightieſt matters of our Eſtate) of adhering to his euill counſels, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that from them wee doe receiue the greateſt contentment that wee can deſire. Yea they haue beene ſo bold and audacious, as that they did dare to preſent a requeſt to our Court of Parliament, vnder the name of our ſaid Brother, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our foreſaid Couſin the Cardinall <hi>Richelieu,</hi> in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as the former, full of falſenes &amp; forged calumnies, contrary to all humanity, reaſon and truth. Which cauſed vs to anſwer our ſaid Brother, and by our letters the 5. of Iune laſt publiſhed in our Chancery, to declare our good intention and meaning, and the exceeding ſatisfaction which we haue receiued by the ſeruice, faithfulneſſe, and good carriage of our aforeſaid Couſin the Cardinall, in ſo many, great, and weighty occaſions, in the which wee haue very profitably employed him for the good and greatneſſe of our State, as alſo from the reſt our chiefe Counſellers. All theſe meanes notwithhanding haue hitherto ſerued onely to make them the more impudent and inſolent, and to continue their enterprizes, and pernicious deſignes, which they had begun and vndertaken, not onely to diuert our ſaid Brother from the obedience which he oweth vs, but alſo he much honored Lady our Mother, who ſince a ſhort ſpace of ime hath ſuffered her ſelfe alſo to be led away and ſeduced by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1230:11"/>their miſchieuous counſels, and to ſide with our brother in his deſignes, more than did well become her. It may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by reaſon of the falſe and euill rumour which ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons haue ſpred, who make profeſſion of curious and euill ſciences, giues them hopes of ſome ready change in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Wee perceiuing all theſe their proceedings, and ſeeing that it was a difficult matter to prouide for the ſafetie of this Kingdome, and our owne perſon, if any longer we ſhould ſuffer them to goe on in theſe deuices, wayes and practices, which they did publiquely attempt euen in our Court, by thoſe which did approach neere vnto them, We thought good at the ſame inſtant when our Brother withdrew himſelfe from vs, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Lady our Mother with the intelligence we had of all their practices and deuices, which they vſed to our great preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and with our reſolution which we had taken for the ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of that courſe; As namely to take into hold and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſome perſons which we knew to participate in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and to baniſh the reſt from our Court. Alſo we deſired &amp; entreated her, to this end, to aſſiſt vs with her beſt counſell, as formerly ſhee had done within theſe few yeares, and to leaue &amp; ſeparate her ſelfe from all the ſecret intelligences, which ſhe had or might haue with our foreſaid Brother, who was then departed from vs. We perſiſted in this our ſupplication euen to <hi>Campaguis,</hi> where we made knowne vnto her diuers other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances by our truſty and welbeloued, the Lord <hi>Chaſtean-newf,</hi> Keeper of the Scale, and our truſty and welbeloued Couſen, the Marſhal <hi>de Schomb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgh,</hi> vnto both which ſhee anſwered, that ſhee was weary any longer to intermeddle with our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, &amp; that ſhe would no more haue any ſhare, nor be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker with our Counſels; which cauſed vs too too confidently to vnderſtand and beleeue, the firme reſolution which ſhe had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to remaine linked and joyned to the deſignes of our ſaid Brother, and to follow and be led by the pernicious counſels which were giuen him. Whereupon we reſolued and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſeparate our ſelues for a while from her, and to entreate her to withdraw herſelfe and retire to <hi>Moulins,</hi> a place which properly belongs vnto her, and which place during the time of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1230:11"/>our minoritie, ſhee voluntarily choſe for her owne abode. Vnto this ſhe gaue anſwer, that then ſhe would willingly goe thither; but a few dayes afterward, ſhee requeſted vs to thinke it expdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and fitting, that ſhee might betake her ſelfe to <hi>Neuers:</hi> Which ſhe was ſo much inclining vnto, and did affect, becauſe ſhe had a deſire to approach and draw neerer to our ſaid Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who was then as yet at <hi>Orleans.</hi> A while after this, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and perceiuing that our ſaid Brother in his proceedings, vſed many deuices and cunning practices, ſtriuing and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring to aſſemble together many warlike troupes, wee inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him by our welbeloued Couſin the Cardinall <hi>de Valette,</hi> to abſent and ſeparate himſelfe from all thoſe wicked counſels, and to returne againe to vs, where we promiſed him that he ſhould receiue all good and fauourable contentment; which he refuſing to doe, and to haue correſpondencie, and to joyne with our good meaning and intention, we journyed as farre as <hi>Eltampes,</hi> where preſently we were informed that he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>Orleans,</hi> ſo to retire and leaue our Kingdome, where he was no ſooner departed, but our ſaid Mother ſent vs word that ſhee would no longer goe, either to <hi>Moulins</hi> or <hi>Neuers,</hi> and that ſhee deſired not to depart out of <hi>Champaguie;</hi> and at the very ſame time ſhee and our ſaid Brother did deuiſe and effect to publiſh and divulge this rumour, that ſhee was detained in priſon, notwithſtanding ſhee had all liberty afforded her with her traine either to goe to <hi>Moulins</hi> or <hi>Neuers,</hi> although in thoſe places there was no Garriſon. But as this ſuppoſed impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment ſerued for a pretence of diſcontentment vnto thoſe that waited for ſuch an occaſion and opportunity, ſo ſhe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued this falſe complaint, notwithſtanding that daily our Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin the Marſhall <hi>Deſtree,</hi> and alſo the Lord Marqueſſe of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Sch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>out</hi> did aduertiſe her in our behalfe (which two wee haue many ſeuerall times ſent vnto her) that ſhee would bee pleaſed to depart out of <hi>Campagnie,</hi> and to chuſe ſuch a place within our Kingdome, as ſhee ſhould thinke moſt fitting for her abiding: offering her (to the end ſhee might abide there with the more reſpect and authority) the gouernment of that Prouince, into the which ſhee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1230:12"/>would betake her ſelfe, forthwith declaring and making known vnto her, that her remaining ſtill in <hi>Champagnie,</hi> gaue vnto vs great cauſe of jealouſie &amp; ſuſpicion, foraſmuch as we were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly enformed they did perſwade her to depart out of our Kingdome, (vnto which ſhee would no way condeſcend, nor thereby be perſwaded) faining many cauſes of complaint, as among others, that we would haue ſent her vnto Italie, and that our Gallyes were ready prepared for the ſame purpoſe. Then wee ſent vnto her our ſaid Couſin, the Marſhall of <hi>Shombergh,</hi> and the Lord <hi>de Roiſſye</hi> Counſellor in our Councell of State, to deſire her to conforme her ſelfe to our will and pleaſure, and to reſolue with herſelfe to depart out of <hi>Champagnie,</hi> and to chooſe ſuch a place within our Kingdome which ſhee might like of for her dwelling, onely <hi>Champagnie</hi> excepted. To the end that thoſe pretences might ceaſe of thoſe who had entiſed our ſaid Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to forſake our Kingdome, and that they might not haue ſo much as any appearance to ground their reports vpon, of our Mothers impriſonment. Nay which is more, they two in our name, proffered vnto her the gouernment of <hi>Anion,</hi> which ſhee complained ſhee was bereaued of, and that the ſame was taken from her, although indeed ſhee had of her owne accord aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned the ſame, for ſome conſiderations beſt knowne to her ſelfe. They vrged alſo vnto her and ſhewed her, that it was very requiſite for the good of our affaires, and that it would proue very aduantagious to her ſelfe if ſhee would be pleaſed to conforme her ſelfe to our will and intentions. But whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reaſons they could lay before her, it was impoſſible to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert and draw her from her ſtrong reſolution, which ſhee had taken to abide in <hi>Champagnie,</hi> for to bring to paſſe the deſigne, which ſince that time ſhee hath executed. Notwithſtanding all this her reſiſtance, to teſtifie more and more our affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, and the earneſt deſire wee haue to re-unite her vnto vs, we cauſed thoſe troupes to be remoued which we had left in <hi>Champagnie,</hi> and ſince that did diuers times ſend to her our ſaid Couſin the Marſhall Deſtree, and the Marquis <hi>de</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Shan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> to reiterate the requeſt which ſo often we had made vnto
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1230:12"/>her, that ſhee would chooſe any other place than <hi>Champagnie</hi> for her abode. Yea we proffered her to come and viſite her in her houſe at <hi>Monceana,</hi> or ſome other place in the way to <hi>Blois, Angers,</hi> or <hi>Moulins</hi> if ſhee went thither, to the end that wee might be reconciled together. This in appearance ſhee ſeemed to agree vnto, and willing to embrace, which gaue vs great contentment, and abundant ſatisfaction, ſuppoſing that this alſo was the way to reduce our ſaid brother to his deuoir, and to remoue all thoſe pretences which the foreſaid euill Authors of bad counſell did make vſe of. But when wee beleeued that our ſaid Mother was well contented with vs, and was moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and willing to follow our good intention, which wee had for our common good, and the good and happineſſe of the whole Kingdome of France, which hope we conceiued by the anſwer deliuered vnto vs by our ſaid Couſin the Marſhall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtree, who brought vs word, that ſhee would neuer depart out of Campagnie, to goe into any other place without our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and conſent. But all this proued but a ſhadow, for in lieu of performance, we vnderſtood that ſhee was departed out of Campagnie the 19. of the laſt Moneth, in a Caroch of the Lady du Freſney, accompanied with the ſaid Lady onely, and one of her Chamber-maidens, and ſo paſſed along to Choſy and Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Court, and there arriued at the Village of Roſny, where ſhe found the Caroch of the Baron of Creuecoeur Gouernour of Auennes, a Towne in the obedience of the King of Spaine, which Gouernour had expected her himſelfe 15. dayes in the Towne of Sein; where being arriued, a Gentleman of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſſe de Vardes told her, that the Lord Vardes the father was arriued at Capelle, and had baniſhed thence his ſonne and his wife; and hereupon ſhee went to Auennes, where ſhee was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and a while after viſited in the behalfe of the Infant by the Prince d'Eſpinoy, Gouernour of Enhault, as ſince that time wee haue learned by the enquirie which wee haue cauſed to bee made, concerning her departure out of our Kingdome, by one of our Maſters of Requeſts, at the very ſame time when ſhee departed from Champagnie. And ſince that to follow the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1230:13"/>ſame courſe which our ſaid Brother had taken, ſhee ſent a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to our ſaid Court of Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> full of forged and calumnious accuſations againſt our ſaid Couſin the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of <hi>Richelien,</hi> very like vnto the ſame which our Brother would haue laid vpon him. Shee was no ſooner arriued at the ſaid place of <hi>Auenues,</hi> but ſhe did preſently write letters vnto vs, full of inuented pretences to colour her departure, and the like complaints againſt our ſaid Couſin the Cardinall, which haue no ground at all nor foundation, but onely ſlanders and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, which doubtleſſe haue beene ſuggeſted vnto her by the Authors of thoſe ſame which our Brother wrote vnto vs; which is euident enough, eſpecially ſince both the one and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe tend to the ſubuerſion of our Authority, and of our Kingdome and State; and wee know that her departure hath beene plotted by thoſe Agents which they haue at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> to cauſe her to retire (as ſhee hath done) into a Countrey vnder the command of the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſhee not reſting contented with the firſt ſlanders and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies which ſhee wrote vnto vs, abuſing our goodneſſe and lenity, and the mildneſſe which hitherto we haue vſed towards them that haue beene the bringers of the ſame, ſhee hath begun to write others and new ſlanders to our ſaid Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to the Prouoſt of the Merchants of our good Citie of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſtriuing to incenſe them againſt vs, and to giue bad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to others.</p>
            <p>Now therefore deſiring to preuent all thoſe euils which may enſue and accrew by the departure of the ſaid Lady our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and our ſaid Brother in this eſtate, and to hinder them that they continue and encreaſe not through the credit which ſome of our Subjects might afford vnto their complaints and inuentions, written and manifeſted to be full of impoſtures, which they publiſh againſt vs, our Gouernment and our prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Miniſters of State; and to the end that none of our ſaid Subjects be not ſo raſh and ill aduiſed as to adhere vnto them, and participate of their euill counſels, to adjoyne vnto them or haue any priuate intelligence with them, or thoſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:1230:13"/>
            <p>Wee doe make knowne by this preſent, that with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of the Princes, Dukes, Peeres, Officers of our Crowne, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> great and eminent perſonages of our Counſell, which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>re about vs, Wee confirming our precedent declarations of 30. of March, and 5. of Iune laſt, haue pronounced and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, and doe pronounce and declare by this preſent, ſigned with our owne hand, guilty of <hi>Crimenlaeſae Majeſtatis,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of our common peace and reſt, all thoſe that ſhall bee found to haue participated to ſuch pernicious and damnable Counſels; or haue withdrawne our ſaid Mother, and our onely Brother the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> from our obedience, and haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticed or inſtigated them to depart out of our Kingdome: As alſo all thoſe that ſhall haue followed them and departed with them, of whatſoeuer ranke or condition they be: with all thoſe that ſhall aſſiſt them, or haue leuied or raiſed any ſouldiers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſeruice, and made any deuices or practices prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to our authority, as well without as within the Kingdome. Wee will therefore, that there be proceeded againſt them as againſt thoſe that are guilty of <hi>Crimenlaeſae Majeſtatis,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of our common peace, according to the rigour of our Lawes, with all the diligence that may bee, both of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Generall, as alſo their Subſtitutes and Deputies.</p>
            <p>And hereby wee prohibite and vtterly forbid all our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of whatſoeuer quality or condition they be, from hauing any intelligence or correſpondencie with our ſaid Mother, and our ſaid Brother, and with their domeſticke ſeruants, and thoſe that are partakers of their Counſels, vnder whatſoeuer pretences it may be.</p>
            <p>And wee wiſh that all their Lordſhips, and whatſoeuer ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable priuiledges they enjoy, mouing vnder our Crowne, be ſeiſed vpon, and afterward re-united to our owne reuenues, that they be depriued of all dignities, places or offices whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they enjoy, And that all their other goods as well moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables as immoueables be ſeiſed and prayſed, afterward to be by vs taken from them and confiſcated. And further we will that all thoſe that leuie any ſouldiers, or maintaine any forces with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1230:14"/>our Commiſſion be earneſtly purſued, and dealt with all according to the rigour of our Lawes and Ordinances, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed becauſe it is a very difficult matter to hinder and preue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſaid Mother and Brother, and ſuch as follow them and adhere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them, from ſending and writing to thoſe, to whom they thinke good; and becauſe it were vnreaſonable and ill-beſeeming, that thoſe to whom they ſend or write vnto, ſhould incurre the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties here preſcribed, Wee will and ordaine, that thoſe to whom theſe Letters ſhall be addreſſed, ſhall be bound as ſoone as euer they ſhall haue receiued the ſame, or as ſoone as any one ſhall come vnto them in their behalfe, to declare it, and carrie thoſe letters to the chiefe Iudge Royall in that Prouince in which they dwell, and cauſe theſe (if they can) to be ſtaid and arreſted, which ſhall bring theſe letters to them, or be truſted with any meſſage to them, which Iudge ſhall be bound inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſend the ſaid letters to the Secretary of State, who hath the deportment of that Prouince. And if this happen in our Court, they ſhall addreſſe themſelues to our beloued and truſty Keeper of the Seale. And if it happen in our Citie of <hi>Paris,</hi> they ſhall be bound to acquaint the Lieutenant of the Citie, and hee ſhall be bound to acquaint vs as ſoone as poſſible may be, and all this vnder the ſame penaltie.</p>
            <p>To this end we will and command all our beloued and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Counſellors, and thoſe of our Court of Parliaments, to cauſe this to be read, publiſhed and regiſtred, and the contents of the ſame to bee executed in euery particular, according to their forme and tenour. As alſo our Proctors Generall to make all diligent and earneſt enquirie, and neceſſary purſuit for the puniſhment of the delinquents. And farther we charge and command all Gouernours, Lieutenants Generall of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, Gouernours and Captaines of our townes and places, to fall vpon all diſobedient and rebels, and to ſuppreſſe them as farre as in them lyes, with their forces which they command for our ſeruice, as alſo in time of neede to aſſemble forces to that end and purpoſe, And all Iudges to execute iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the offendor. And the Prouoſts of our beloued Couſins
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1230:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Marſhals of France, to fall vpon their Camps, and aſſault <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſe, that contrary to our prohibitions, ſhall leuy any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> without Commiſſion expreſſely ſigned by Vs, and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by one of our Secretaries of State, and ſealed with the Great Seale; To execute and fully proceede in iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe they ſhall apprehend, and cut in pieces thoſe who after they haue beene ſummoned, ſhall goe about to ſtand in their defence. For ſuch is our Will and Pleaſure.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>In witneſſe whereof Wee haue cauſed our Seale to bee put to theſe preſents. <hi>Giuen at Paris</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 12. <hi>of Auguſt, in the yeare of Grace,</hi> 1631. <hi>and of our Reigne the</hi> 22. <hi>yeare.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed <hi>Lowys.</hi> and ſomewhat lower by the King.</signed> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>De Lemene.</hi> and Sealed with the great Seale in Yellow waxe.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Reade, publiſhed, and regiſtred, heard at the requeſt of the Atturney Generall of the King, Copied according to the Originall, ſent forth therewont.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>At Paris in the Parliament of the King. <date>
                        <hi>Auguſt</hi> 13. 1631.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
